Guide to the Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project Records 1931-1954
Montana Historical Society Archives
Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project Records
1931-1954
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 7
Buffalo Rapids Project (U.S.)
2.5 linear feet of shelf space
The Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project was an eastern Montana irrigation project that was funded by the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation and the Work Projects Administration. The collection includes subject files of Noel Carrico, a Glendive, Montana, contract negotiator; and Frank L. Patterson, president of the Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association. Included are general correspondence (1931-1954), clippings, legal documents, maps, statistical and financial records, and printed publications. Prominent correspondents include Montana senators Burton K. Wheeler, and James E. Murray, and Congressman James F. O'Connor.
In 1932, a group of eastern Montana farmers, ranchers, and businessmen formed the Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association to investigate ways of ameliorating the prevailing drought conditions. They were especially interested in the possibility of irrigating the agricultural lands along the Yellowstone River between Glendive and Miles City. The Association's organizers began corresponding with other states that had similar irrigation projects. After raising $6,000 from Custer, Prairie, and Dawson County residents, the group subsequently obtained funds under the National Industrial Recovery Act for a Bureau of Reclamation investigation on the proposed Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project. Based upon the Bureau's report, the 18,000-acre Glendive Unit (Division No. 1) was organized in 1937, and received a $1,600,000 federal allotment. Construction began that same year on the main canal and work was completed in 1941. Construction of lateral canals was completed two years later. In 1939, a second division of the project, encompassing the Terry, Fallon, and Shirley Units along the Yellowstone's south bank and consisting of 11,600 acres, was approved under the Great Plains Act. However, due to the shortage of materials during World War II, construction of the Fallon Unit was stopped altogether and work on the other two units was permitted only to the extent that materials became available. The Shirley and Terry Units were completed in 1944, but it was not until August 1945 that War Production Board controls on new construction were lifted, and contracts were awarded for the Fallon Unit.
Content Description:
The records consist of subject files for the Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project, the Fort Peck Dam, the Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association, the Montana Reclamation Association, Frank L. Patterson, and development of the Yellowstone River Basin. The files, arranged chronologically, include correspondence, clippings, legal documents, maps, statistical and financial records, and printed publications. The records are those of Noel Carrico, Glendive, a contract negotiator for the project, and Frank L. Patterson, Terry, president of the Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association. Prominent correspondents include Montana Senators Burton K. Wheeler and James E. Murray and Congressman James F. O'Connor.
Arrangement:
by series
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Buffalo Rapids Project (U.S.)
Fort Peck Dam (Mont.); Glendive (Mont.); Yellowstone River Valley--Agriculture
Federal Government; Irrigation--Montana
Montana; Irrigation
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Subject Files
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes publications on irrigation in Arizona and Nevada; State Engineer John S. James' report on water rights law; proposal by Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association for Buffalo Rapids Project), 1932-1933 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes outgoing correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil; petition for organization of Frenchtown Irrigation District; description of project; Public Works Docket 1701 supplement), 1934-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil with Congressmen and other public officials, companies, and civic interest groups; list of land owners), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 3-9)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil with Congressmen; court papers including petitions, bonds, etc.), January 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil with Congressmen and other public officials, members of the public, etc.; court papers, including order, notice of appropriation of water right; list of land owners; list of property affected; map), February-December 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 1-5)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil with Congressmen, Works Progress Administration, and others; minutes of Federal Irrigation Congress annual meeting in Sidney, Montana; court papers, including petition), 1939 (Box-folder 2 / 6-12)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil with Congressmen and other public officials, public interest groups, etc.; resolution of State-wide meeting of Chamber of Commerce; grants of easements; consents to inclusion; report on use of bentonite in dam construction), 1940 (Box-folder 3 / 1-8)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes deeds; affidavits of signature on petition; resolutions of National Reclamation Association; petition; option for purchase of land by Farm Security Administration; lists of landowners; map), 1940, undated (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neill; court papers including consents to inclusion, order, petition for second district, instructions to judges; description of lands within second district), 1941, undated (Box-folder 4 / 1-3)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil; court papers including consents to inclusion, order, petition for second district, instructions to judges; description of lands within second district), 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil; notice of irrigation district election; application for public official surety bonds), 1946 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil; resolution of Buffalo Rapids Farms Association; notice of election), 1949 (Box-folder 4 / 6-7)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil; resolutions of Buffalo Rapids Irrigation District; lease with Bureau of Reclamation to operate project), 1950 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Buffalo Rapids Irrigation Project (includes correspondence of Desmond J. O'Neil), 1951-1953 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Fort Peck Dam (includes correspondence of Noel Carrico with Cecil W. Smith and others; lists of construction materials; description of dam; clippings; statements of various organizations in support of Fort Peck Dam), 1934-1938 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
  - Fort Peck Dam (includes correspondence of Noel Carrico; brochures on dam; Bureau of Reclamation circulars on power needs in eastern Montana; minutes of Missouri Basin Inter-Agency Committee; Corps of Engineers presentations), 1951-1954 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
  - Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association (includes correspondence of Noel Carrico with J.L. Taylor, government officials, etc.; clippings), 1933-1935 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association (includes Bureau of Reclamation memos; clippings), 1936-1937 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association (includes Bureau of Reclamation invitation for bids and specifications; clippings; Noel Carrico correspondence), 1938 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
  - Mid-Yellowstone Recovery Association (includes Bureau of Reclamation description of project; clippings; Noel Carrico correspondence; "Montana's Planning Organization and its Progress to Date"; annotated list of key people in Dawson, Custer, and Prairie counties; statistics on livestock shipments; Dawson County map), 1940-1943 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
  - Montana Reclamation Association (includes proceedings; bylaws; bulletins; Congressional report on Missouri Valley Authority Act), 1943-1945 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Montana Reclamation Association (includes brochures; "Balanced Use Development of River Basins," by Roland Renne; "Conservation of the Natural Resources of Montana and their Use by the Stockman," by Milton C. Simpson; National Reclamation Association bulletin; "U.S. Forest Service: Progress in Montana during 1949," by Montana Reclamation Association; "What Are We Doing to Keep Our Water?" by State Engineer's Office), 1948-1949 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Montana Reclamation Association (includes brochures re valley authorities; resolutions by National Reclamation Association; "Wildlife in the Reclamation Program," by F.A. Wenstrom; reports of activities of the Corps of Engineers in various districts; "The Reclamation Program for Fiscal Year 1951 in Montana and North Dakota," by Bureau of Reclamation), January-November 1950 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
  - Montana Reclamation Association (includes "Sportsman's View of Land and Water Resource Development," by Montana Wildlife Federation; articles by H.L. Dusenberry; "Missouri River Basin Project in Montana, Fiscal Year 1950," by Bureau of Reclamation), November-December 1950 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Montana Reclamation Association (includes National Reclamation Association and Montana Reclamation Association news bulletins; resolutions by National Reclamation Association; "A National Water Policy," by National Reclamation Association; "Irrigation Pays: Projects Constructed by State Water Conservation Board," by Montana Reclamation Association), 1951-1954 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes National Reclamation Association brochures; clippings; reports on Terry-Fallon Unit #2; correspondence of Patterson, W.B. Vennard, and others; National Recovery Association congressional summary), 1938 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes correspondence of Patterson, W.B. Vennard, and others with Congressmen, Northern Pacific Railway, and others; Congressional bills; National Recovery Association news bulletins; "Report of Terry Delegate to Washington, D.C."; "Soil Survey: the Lower Yellowstone Valley Area, Montana," by William DeYoung), 1939 (Box-folder 5 / 7-9)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes correspondence of Patterson, W.B. Vennard, and others with Congressmen, Northern Pacific Railway, and others; Congressional bills), 1940 (Box-folder 5 / 10-11)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes correspondence of Patterson with Miles City Chamber of Commerce, Montanans Inc. Reclamation Committee; also includes press releases of U.S. Bureau of Reclamation), 1941 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes correspondence of Patterson with Congressmen; Montanans Inc. Reclamation Committee bulletin; speech of Charles H. Leavy re war demands for food and fiber; statement by War Relocation Authority re placement of Japanese evacuees), 1942 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes correspondence of Patterson with Congressmen and Miles City Chamber of Commerce; hearings on U.S. Wartime Reclamation Act; resolution of Prairie County Board of Commissioners re bridge over Yellowstone River at Fallon), 1943-1944 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (includes clippings, Congressional bills, press releases, brochures, ownership list for Buffalo Rapids Irrigation District #2, maps, charts), undated (Box-folder 6 / 4)
  - Frank L. Patterson files (telegrams), undated (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - Yellowstone River Basin development (includes "Preliminary Report Yellowstone River Basin Resume of Possible Development for Flood Control, Irrigation, Navigation, Power, Recreation," by John T. Tucker; resolutions of meeting re formation of Yellowstone River Drainage Basin Association; clippings; minutes of annual meeting of Montana Association of Commercial Organization Secretaries; copies of letters of R. Arnold Sunstrom and H.W. Bashore; "Postwar Planning," by J.C. Thomson), 1937-1943 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Yellowstone River Basin development (includes National Reclamation Association bulletins; copy of letter of Franklin D. Roosevelt; statement of Harry W. Bashore; statement of governors of Montana, North Dakota and Wyoming; House document 475 re Missouri River Basin; clippings; extract of proceedings on "Rivers and Harbors Bill"; correspondence; Congressional bills; remarks of Joseph C. O'Mahoney at Water Conservation Conference; maps), 1944-1945 (Box-folder 6 / 7-8)
  - Yellowstone River Basin development (includes Public Utilities newsletter; "Fish and Wildlife Resources in Relation to the Missouri River Basin," by Rudolph Dieffenbach; statement of Harry E. Polk; excerpts from address by South Dakota Governor M.Q. Sharpe; National Reclamation Association Bulletin; clippings; maps), 1946 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Yellowstone River Basin development (includes Bureau of Reclamation circulars; Idaho State Reclamation Association circulars; Missouri River Basin progress reports; National Water Conservation Conference resolutions; clippings; maps), 1947 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
  - Yellowstone River Basin development (includes Bureau of Reclamation circulars; Congressional bills; Yellowstone Basin Association resolutions; speeches of Hugh Butler, R.W. Booze, Walt Horan, Harry E. Polk, and Fred G. Aandahl; clippings), 1948-1954 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
- Transfers
  - List of photographs, published material, and maps transferred to Photograph Archives, Library, and Library Map Collection respectively (Box-folder 6 / 12)